Musaylimah(مسيلمة) was firm and he was in the heart of his army
and his people were surrounding him from each direction,
it was like a hurricane with Musaylimah(مسيلمة) in the middle, and they're just revolving around him and fighting.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) realized that there is no chance, we can stop these people from dying.
Because they were just dropping down dead; Banu Hanifa(بنوحنيفة), and the fight still going on.
He realized that the only way is to get through to Musailimah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمة ألكذاب)
Musaylimah(مسيلمة) was the heart of his army.
I mean, when At-Tabari(ألطبري) describes it, he says,
Musaylimah(مسيلمة) stood firm, he was the eye of the storm, their mill revolved around him,
it was like a mill revolving and he was the center, he was the eye of the storm.
So Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) he took with him a group of Fursaan(فُرسان), knights.
And he said: Let's just charge straightforward; break through their ranks
until we get to Musaylimah(مسيلمة) himself and kill him.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) even though, he's the Ameer(أمير) of the Army, he's the head of the army.
He would just strike straight through the ranks of the enemy, cut it like a knife, cutting a loaf of bread.
So Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and his Fursaan(فُرسان) on top of their horses
just broke through the ranks of the enemy, until they could see Musaylimah(مسيلمة) in front of their eyes.
When that happened, Musaylimah(مسيلمة) and his army retreated.
And the Muslims just followed them killing them left and right in their retreat
until they cornered them into a garden, a farm or ranch that was fortified.
So Musaylimah(مسيلمة) and his people got into this ranch, they locked the gates.
So now the Muslims were locked outside and unable to get in.
Al-Bara'a Bin Malik(ألبرآءبن مالك) the brother of Anas Ibn Malik(أنس إبن مالك), he said:
Throw me in, just throw me in.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he ordered Al-Bara'a(ألبراء) to join an army.
But he sent with him a letter to the Ameer(أمير) of the army saying,
Do not appoint Al-Bara'a(ألبراء) over any position of leadership
because he will perish everyone with him.
Anybody with Al-Bara'a(ألبراء) would just die.
Don't give him any position of leadership, Let him do what he wants on his own
but don't appoint him as a leader.
Al-Bara'a(ألبراء) said just throw me on top of them.
So they said: We're not going to do that.
He said: I tell you, throw me.
So, they put him on top of shield, they just picked him up.
In one narration, they just threw him.
In another narration, it says that they picked him up
and when he saw the army of Musaylimah(مسيلمة) right under him
he hesitated and he pulled back,
he just saw a flood of people with the swords pointing up
and then he took a breath and he said throw me.
So they threw him in and the people of Musaylimah(مسيلمة), see this man falling down on them like a bird from the sky.
He succeeded in fighting them away until, he gets to the gate.
He opens the gate, picks up the keys and allows the Muslim army to come in
and he had 80 injuries in his body or something like that.
The Muslims came in and now there's nowhere to go.
The army of Musaylimah(مسيلمة) and the army of Khalid(خالد) are within this locked ranch.
There is nothing to do but fight to death
and now Musaylimah(مسيلمة) his Jin(جن) was coming to him.
They say: When his Jin(جن) would come to him, the foam would come out of his mouth
and he would be obsessed with that Jin(جن),
he had to throw himself to a wall and his eyes were just roaming around.
At that moment Wahshee(وحشي) the killer of Hamza(حمزه)
Wahshee(وحشي), the one who killed Hamza(حمزه), but later on became Muslim.
He said: Just as I have killed the most beloved servant of Allah
I'm going to compensate for that by killing the enemy of Allah.
So he made it his target, that he's gonna use his skill to kill Musailimah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمة ألكذاب).
And he was very skilled in the Lances, throwing the spear.
So he got him in his sights and he was able to strike Musailimah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمة ألكذاب)
but at the same time Abu Dujana Al-Ansaari(أبودجانه ألأنصاري)
the one who had the red band on his head in the Battle of Badr(بدر), took a hit at Musaylimah(مسيلمة).
So it wasn't clear, who killed him and Wahshee(وحشي) would later on say, Our Lord knows who really killed him.
But both of them took a strike at Musaylimah(مسيلمة)
and because of that Musaylimah(مسيلمة) was dead,
it was the spear of Wahshee(وحشي) and the sword of Abu Dujana(أبودجانة).
With the death of Musaylimah(مسيلمة), the entire thing was over, that was the was the end.
Musaylimah(مسيلمة) was the center in which the mill was revolving around.
That garden was called Hadeeqa Tul Moat(حديقةالموت), the garden of death.
The slogan of the Muslims on that day was
Waa Muhammadah(وامحمداة), or Ya Muhammadah(يا محمداة).
They were calling the name of Muhammadﷺ.
Now, the calling of the name was symbolic, it was a slogan
it didn't mean that they were asking him for help
because we know that that's something we're not allowed to do.
But the Muslims had slogans in their wars.
In one of these Saraya(سراية) Abu Salamah(أبوسلمة) says our slogan was
Ammet(أمت), Ammet(أمت), kill, kill.
In this battle, it was Ya Muhammadah(يا محمداة)
that was their slogan in the battle.
There were ten thousand among the enemy killed, inside the garden.
The number of Muslims, who were killed in the garden of death was 600.
The total number of Muslims killed was 1200, so 600 in the garden and 600 outside.
There are a few heroic acts that we need to talk about.
Abu Aqeel(أبوعقيل) one of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار), he was one of the first who were injured in the battle.
He was struck by an arrow between his shoulder and his heart.
It did not kill him, but it left his left side of the body weak.
So he had to take rest in a tent, prepared for the injured.
He heard Ma'an Bin Qais(معن بن قيس), make a call
يا للأنصار الله الله
O Ansaar(أنْصَار) Allah Allah, Allah Allah,
ألقرَّة  على عداء الله
Attack the enemies of Allah.
Abu Aqeel(أبوعقيل), he tried to stand up and picked up his sword.
So the Sahabah(صحابه) told him what are you doing?
He said: Ma'an(معن) has called my name.
They said: He didn't call your name, he's calling the Ansaar(أنْصَار).
He said: I am one of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار).
They said: Well, you're injured there's no fighting for you.
He said: I am one of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار) and I heard my name was called
and I am going to respond to the call even if I have to crawl.
And he picked up his sword and he went to fight and he can't use his left hand to protect himself.
So now he was fighting without protection and he was injured and he fell down.
And towards his last moments before he died, Abdullah Ibn Umar رضي الله عنه approached him.
So Abu Aqeel(أبوعقيل) said: Who does this day belong to? Who does this day belong to?
Ibn Umar(إبن عُمَر) said;
أبشِر فقد قتل عدوالله
Rejoice because the enemy of Allah was killed.
Abu Aqeel(أبوعقيل) said: Al-Hamdulillah(ألحمدلله) and then he passed away.
All what he wanted to know, who does that day belong to?
Does it belong to the Muslims, or does it belong to Musaylimah(مسيلمة)?
And when he knew that the enemy of Allah was killed? He said: Al-Hamdulillah(ألحمدلله)!
Nusaibah Bint Ka'ab(نصيبة بنت كعب), she made an oath that she's not going to lay down her sword
unless Musaylimah(مسيلمة) is killed and she participated in the fighting, the actual fighting.
Nusaibah Bint Ka'ab(نصيبة بنت كعب) was left with 12 injuries.
So she had to be tended to, in a tent
and she said that Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه took so much care for me.
He sent me a doctor, who would tend to my injuries and they use boiling oil to seal my injuries.
She said: I would rather have my limbs amputated, then go through that pain.
To seal the injury and to clean it from any infections.
They would pour boiling oil to just burn the entire injury
that was their medical treatment of the day.
Obviously without any anesthesia without any painkillers - Allah O Akbar(الله أكبر)!
Just think about a woman fighting and being injured and then she has to go through all of this pain.
And now the Ummah(امة) men and women are laid back and relaxed
and not realizing their duties towards Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, not willing to suffer any pain, for the religion of Allah.
The Sahabah رضي الله عنهم for them Islam was not lip service and talk.
It was struggling, it was effort and it was some physical pain.
They went through a lot of physical pain.
I mean, imagine what Nusaibah Bint Ka'ab(نصيبة بنت كعب) went through.
If one of your teeth will be plucked out without any painkiller.
You would be thinking a lot before you go to the dentist.
Now, Nusaibah Bint Ka'ab(نصيبة بنت كعب) took the decision to fight
and she knew very well that there are some consequences of that.
First of all, the injury itself is very painful and then to cure it, is very painful too
but they took that decision consciously.
Because they would rather do that for Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ then suffer on the Day of Judgment.
نسعل الله عزوجل أن يقيم من عذاب
We ask Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to spare us from all punishment.
And note here on the role that women used to play.
Nusaibah Bint Ka'ab(نصيبة بنت كعب) participated in actual fighting
tells you a lot about the role of early Muslim women.
Also Umm Tamim(أم تميم) the wife of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was given the responsibility of guarding a prisoner of war.
So in addition to their supportive roles of nursing, and providing food, and supplements to the army
there were also some combative roles
like what Nusaibah Bint Ka'ab(نصيبة بنت كعب) was involved in
and also the security guard role
that Umm Tamim(أم تميم), the wife of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) had.
The Shuhadaa(شهداء) of the battle of Al-Yamamah(أليمامة)
Thabit Bin Qais رضي الله عنه,
one who held the banner of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار).
The one, who set his foot in the ground, so that he would not retreat, he was killed.
One of the Muslim soldiers saw a dream after Thabit(ثابت) was killed.
This was mentioned by Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر), in this dream Thabit(ثابت) comes to him and tells him
when I was killed a Muslim came to me and took away a very valuable shield that I have.
And this Muslim is in such and such place, you'll find his horse next to it.
And then you'll find my shield on top of it is a rock and on top of it, is a saddle.
Go and take my shield, give it to Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
and tell him to send it to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and to have him sell it, to pay my debts
that belongs to so and so.
And then Thabit(ثابت) told this man in the dream.
وإيَّاك أن تقول هذا حُلُم فتضيهَا
And be aware to say that this is a dream, so I'm going to neglect it.
He said: This is serious.
So the man wakes up and he goes and just as I was described in the dream he finds the shield
and he takes it to Khalid(خالد), Khalid(خالد) sends it to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) sells it and they pay off the debt of Thabit(ثابت).
So his will was given after his death.
He gave his will after his death.
It's a Karamah(كرامة) for Thabit Bin Qais(ثابت بن قيس)
because you know that you are held captive and you cannot enter into Jannah(جنة)
until you pay your debts.
Zaid Ibn Khattab رضي الله عنه the brother Umar(عُمَر).
When the news reached Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه, he said;
رحم الله زيد، سبقني إلى الحُسنَيين، أسلم قبلي، واستُشهد قبلي
May Allah have mercy on Zaid(زيد), he came first before me, in the two greatest things
becoming a Muslim and becoming Shaheed(شَهِيد).
He became a Muslim before me and he became a Shaheed(شَهِيد) before me.
Obviously Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was happy that his brother died as a Shaheed(شَهِيد) but
because when Abdullah Ibn Umar رضي الله عنه came back from the Ghazwa(غزوة)
as soon as he came in and met his father.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told him;
Abdullah(عبدالله)! How dare you show me your face?
Why didn't you die as a Shaheed(شَهِيد) as your uncle died?
This tells you a lot about the Tarbiyah(تربية) of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
and the Tarbiyah(تربية) of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم to their children.
He didn't hug him and say, Al-hamdulillah(ألحمدلله) you came back safe.
I wish that you didn't even go out, you disobeyed me, by going out to fight.
He said: How dare you show me your face.?
When your uncle died as a Shaheed(شَهِيد) and you didn't.
Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) said: O Father, I asked for it.
But Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ blessed my uncle with it.
And Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ decided that I would live for another day.
So Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه was happy that his brother has died as a Shaheed(شَهِيد).
But still, it left a very significant scar on the heart of Umar(عُمَر)
and he would always remember his brother.
In fact, whenever the wind would blow from the North.
Ar-Reeh-Us-Suba(ألريح صبح)
because the battle happened in Al-Yamamah(أليمامة), which is North.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Whenever the wind would blow from the north,
it would remind me my brother Zaid(زيد).
Mutammum Bin Nuwairah(متمم بن نويرة), the brother of Malik(مالك), who was killed by Khalid(خالد).
He made some lines of poetry talking about his brother.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) when he heard those lines. He said;
I wish that I had that ability to say poetry if I did, I would say similar words.
In the obituary of my brother.
Mutammam(متمم) told Umar(عُمَر), he said;
لو أنَّ أخي ذهب على ما ذهب عليه أخوك ما حزنة عليه
If my brother died the same way for the same cause your brother died.
I wouldn't have had any sadness for him, I wouldn't have regretted his death.
Your brother died as a Shaheed(شَهِيد).
If my brother Malik(مالك) died in the same situation for the same cause that your brother died,
I wouldn't have had any regret.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
ما عزاني أحد بمثل ما أذيتنى به
No one has ever given me counsel like you did.
Nobody has given me condolences, like you did.
This is the best thing I've ever heard.
The fact that my brother dies is a Shaheed(شَهِيد).
I shouldn't have any sadness or sorrow because of that.
The brother of Zaid(زيد)
the brotherhood that was made between Muhajireen(مهاجرين) Wal Ansaar(ولأنْصَار) in Madina
was Ma'an Bin Udae(معان بن عدي),
Rasool Ullah appointed Zaid Ibn Khattab(زيد إبن خطاب) to be the brother of Ma'an Bin Udae(معان بن عدي).
Now, we know that that brotherhood of Al-Akhuwa(ألأخوة)
that was instituted as soon as Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) went into Madina was later abrogated.
Because it was a brotherhood that was put ahead of Brotherhood of Blood.
So even in terms of inheritance, they would inherit each other, that was abrogated.
However, the relationship between many of these brothers continued on, to be a special relationship
and this was the case between Zaid(زيد) and Ma'an(معان).
They continue to having that very close friendship, until the last day.
So Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, His Qadar(قَدَر) was that they die the same day.
So Ma'an Bin Udae(معان بن عدي) died in that battle.
Ma'an Bin Udae(معان بن عدي), he had a very amazing statement when Rasool Allah ﷺ died.
Some of the Sahabah(صحابه) said: We wish that we have died before Rasool Allah ﷺ died.
Ma'an Bin Udae(معان بن عدي) said: I would not desire that
because I want to believe in Muhammadﷺ dead as I believed him alive.
I wanted to believe in Muhammadﷺ when he is dead, just as I believed in him when he was alive.
Abdullah Bin Suhail Bin Amr(عبدالله بن سهيل بن عمرو) also was a Shaheed(شَهِيد).
Sohail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو) was the one, who signed the contract with Rasool Allah ﷺ in Hudaybiyah(حديبية).
His son Abdullah(عبدالله) was one of the Muslims
who were handed over to the Mushrikeen(مشركين) according to the terms of the agreement, Abdullah(عبدالله).
The terms of the agreement of Al-Hudaybiyah(ألحديبية) stated that
if a Muslim comes from Makkah to Madina, he should be returned.
But if an apostate goes from Madina to Makkah they are not returned.
Abdullah(عبدالله) was a Muslim who came from Makkah to Madina
and according to the terms of the agreement, he had to be returned.
So he stayed in Makkah and was persecuted.
He came out with the Mushrikeen(مشركين) in the Battle of Badr(بدر).
He came alongside the army and as soon as they reached the battleground,
he ran away and joined the Muslims.
He died as a Shaheed(شَهِيد) in this battle.
Abu Dujana(أبودجانة), the one with the red band on the Badr(بدر),
who was marching in front of the army with pride.
So as a Muslim you're not supposed to be arrogant.
And that was a very arrogant way of walking.
So some of the Muslims were wondering. Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ dislikes this way of walking except in this situation
because he's doing it to terrify the enemy of Allah.
Abu Dujana(أبودجانة) was the partner of Wahshee(وحشي) in killing Musaylimah(مسيلمة)
He also died in this battle.
At-Tufail Bin Amr Ad-Dausi(ألطفيل بن عمرو ألدؤسي) was the chief of his people Daus(دؤس).
He was with his son Amr(عمرو) and he told him: O son, I saw a dream.
I saw that my head was shaven, and a bird came out from my mouth.
And a womb of a woman swallowed me.
he said: My son, I interpret that to mean Shahadah(شَهَادَة).
The shaving of my head is my killing, and the bird coming out from my mouth is my soul.
And the woman swallowing me in her womb, is the earth, I will be buried
and his dream was fulfilled in the Battle of Yamamah(يمامة).
Abbad Bin Bishr(عبَّادبن بشر) one of the notables among Al-Ansaar رضي الله عنهم
he was part of the Special Operations team that assassinated Ka'ab Ibn Al-Ashraf(كعب إبن ألأشرف).
One night Rasool Allah ﷺ was praying Tahajjud(تهجد) late at night
and the room of Ayesha(عائشه) was adjacent to the Masjid(مسجد).
So Rasool Allah ﷺ was hearing the recitation of Qur'an come from Al-Masjid(مسجد).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: O Ayesha(عائشه) is this the voice of Abbad(عَبَّاد)?
Ayesha(عائشه) said: Yes! Rasool Allah ﷺ said: May Allah have mercy on him
and this is in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
And usually when Rasool Allah ﷺ would make a Dua(دُعَا), for Allah to have mercy on someone
what would happen to that person? He dies as a Shaheed(شَهِيد)
as if mercy of Allah is Shahadah(شَهَادَة).
Because once there was one of the Ansaar(أنْصَار), who was making Anasheed(أناشيد) for the army.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: May Allah have mercy on him
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: O Rasool Ullah
لَو لَا متعتنا به
O Rasool Ullah
We wanted to enjoy him, meaning you have taken away his life now.
We wanted to enjoy him.
So the Dua(دُعَا) of Rahma(رحمة) by Rasool Allah ﷺ means that the person will die as a Shaheed(شَهِيد).
He also saw dreams. So Karamaat(كرامات) and dreams happen a lot to the Mujahideen(مجاهدين)
because of the Sidq(صدق)
أصدقكم حديثًا أصدقكم رُؤيَّا
The most truthful of you in words are the most true in their dreams.
Their dreams are not deceptive, their dreams are true.
And a person who is in the path of Allah fighting in the sake of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ represents truth
because you are giving up your life for Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
So he saw a dream that, he told one of his companions, he said;
I saw a dream that the sky opened, the heavens opened and I went through and then it closed
and I interpret that to mean Shahadah(شَهَادَة).
He saw that after the Battle of buzakha(بزاخة), which we talked about with Tulaiha(طليحة)
and the dream was fulfilled.
During the battle Abbad Bin Bishr(عبَّادبن بشر),
he went on top of a hill and called Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار), so now you mobilize your own people.
The Ansaar(أنْصَار), they give motivation to the Ansaar(أنْصَار), and Muhajiroon(مهاجرون) because it's competition
nobody wants to be the one, who will be the cause of the defeat of the Muslims
and every tribe that would call on their own people.
So now Abbad Bin Bishr(عبَّادبن بشر) is trying to motivate Al-Ansaar(اَلْاَنْصَار)
he stood up on a hill, so they could all see him and he called them.
So, a big group of them came to him and what he did is,
he took the Sheath of his sword and he broke it on his knees.
So, when the Ansaar(أنْصَار) saw that they broke theirs and that means this sword is not going back.
And he said: Go ahead with truth, and they attacked
and many of them were killed in that attack, he was killed at the age of 45.
Abbad Bin Bishr(عبَّادبن بشر) with his group played a very important role, in pushing the people of Musaylimah(مسيلمة) into the farm.
And then they went in and fought with them, in closed gates.
Abbad Bin Bishr(عبَّادبن بشر) did so much that day in fighting
that he became an example later on among Banu Hanifa(بنوحنيفة).
Whenever they would see somebody injured
they would say you're injured by the Mujarrib(مُجَرِّب) the experienced man, Abbad Bin Bishr(عبَّادبن بشر).
His fighting on that day became an example for the people,
رضي الله عنه وَاَرضاہ
So the battle was over.
Now Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) wants to see this man, who was root of the whole problem, Musaylimah(مسيلمة).
So he took with him with Muja'ah(مجاعة),
who was Muja'ah(مجاعة)?
His captive, the hostage.
Who's in the tent of his wife.
So now he's holding Muja'ah(مجاعة), and they're strolling through the dead bodies.
And Khalid(خالد) wants to know, who's Musaylimah(مسيلمة)
so they pass next to Ar-Rajjal(ألرجال) and he says, this is Ar-Rajjal Bin Unfua(ألرجال بن عنفوة).
And then they go on and they enter into the garden of death.
And then Muja'ah(مجاعة) points to Musailimah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمة ألكذاب)
when Khalid(خالد) takes a look at this man, he said: This is the one,
ألَّذي فعل بكم لأفاعيل
This is the one, who did to you what he did.?
The way he looks, doesn't reflect what evil and influence, he has caused.
So Muja'ah(مجاعة) said: Yes, this is the one.
Muja'ah(مجاعة) told Khalid(خالد) that I want to strike a deal with you, for my people,
Banu Hanifa(بنوحنيفة) were different clans a conglomeration of Clans.
So Muja'ah(مجاعة) tells Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
I want to make a truce with you for my people.
I pay you this amount of gold, silver and armory.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) could continue fighting
because he sent his army to just pick up the many of the other fortresses.
Take all of the women and children and wealth, all of it.
But Muja'ah(مجاعة) he told Khalid(خالد) there are many fighters in my fortress.
So let me strike a deal with you, this is what I will pay you.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said: Alright, go and discuss with your people, so he goes
Muja'ah(مجاعة) goes into his fortress, there are no men,
except the elderly and the weak, women and children.
He told them all to dress up in armory
and he told the women to take out their hair on their chest
because men in those days used to grow their hair long.
So he told the women to hang their hair and to wear turbans and helmets and armory
and carry weapons and to stand on top of the roofs and on the guarding points of this fort.
And Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), he is in a distance.
So, the Muslims cannot see the faces.
So Muja'ah(مجاعة) comes back and tells Khalid(خالد) my people refused.
But let me try another deal with them, so he reduced the amount and said;
I'll go and try with my people.
And they're ready to fight you and take a look.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) takes a look.
A blanket of black, is all what he sees covering the roofs.
Now Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was exhausted from fighting and his army were weak.
Because the Battle of Al-Yamamah(أليمامة) was the most vicious battle that the Muslims have been in so far.
1200 Muslims were killed.
That was the biggest single day loss ever, for the muslims.
About 300 of Al-Muhajireen(مهاجرين) Wal-Ansaar(واَلْاَنْصَار)
about 60 or 50 from Haffaz Al-Qur'an(حفاظ ألقرآن) were killed on that day.
So even though the news of victory reached to Madina
but the news of the dead, subdued the tone of happiness
because it was the greatest loss that the Muslims have ever suffered so far.
Now the losses among Banu Hanifa(بنوحنيفة) were greater, I mean, 10,000 were killed in the garden of death,
let alone the ones were killed outside.
So the Muslims are exhausted, tired, and they needed rest.
So now Khalid(خالد) takes a look at this blanket of people covering the roofs.
He said: Fine, I agree.
Muja'ah(مجاعة) said: Let's write it down.
They write it down and he opens the gates.
The Muslims go in, there's nobody but children and women.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said: You tricked me.
Muja'ah(مجاعة) said: I did what I have to do to save my people.
These are my kinship.
I did, what I have to do.
Khalid(خالد) told Muja'ah(مجاعة) marry me, your daughter.
Muja'ah(مجاعة) said: That will ruin my reputation and ruin yours, with your leader.
Khalid(خالد) Said: Man! I'm telling you to marry me, your daughter.
He said: Fine, I marry you, my daughter.
The news reaches to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
that Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) has married again.
He sends a letter. He says;
يابن أم خالد إنك لفارغ تنكح النساء وبفناء بيتك دم ألف ومائتي رجل من المسلمين
لم يجفف بعد ثم خذعك مجاعة راعيك فصالحك عن قومه وقد أمكن الله منهم
O son of the mother of Khalid(خالد)!
You find yourself free to marry women.
When in your court yard is the blood of 1200 Muslims and their blood did not dry yet.
And then you allow Maja'ah(مجاعة) to trick you, when Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has handed them over to you.
So it was a very stern letter and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was very upset رضي الله عنه.
When Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) reads the letter, he says:
This is the work of the Left Handed man, meaning Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب),
who was left handed.
He said, this the work of the Left Handed man and he writes a letter. He says:
أمَّا بَعد، فل امري ما تزوجت نساء حتى تمَّالِيَّ السُّرُور وكرت به دار
I did not marry, until the victory was done.
Meaning we're celebrating victory, our victory is done
and that's when I married I didn't marry while the fighting was raging and going on.
وما تزوجت اِلَّا المرِاة لو عملت عليه من المدينة خاتمًا لم أبالي
دعنِّي إستفرت خطبتي إليه من تحت قدمه
He said: And I married the daughter of a man, whom if I was in Madina
it would be worth traveling all the way to marry his daughter.
But I was right there, next to him.
He was saying that Maja'ah(مجاعة) is a person among his people.
He is a man, whom I would even travel from Madina all the way to him, to marry his daughter
his character and his position, and Khalid(خالد) says:
فإن كنت قد قحتلي ذالك لدين أو لدنيا أعتكتك
If you had a justification, a religious or worldly justification for that
then you could be excused for blaming me for it.
So, he is saying that, there is no reason to be angry with, what I did.
And then he said;
وأمَّا حسن عزائي عن قتل المسلمين فولله لو كان حزن يقي حياًّ أو يَرُدُّوْ مَيَّتًا لا أبقى حسن الحيَّ وَرَدِّ الْمَيِت
In terms of my sadness for the dead Muslims.
If sadness would resurrect them from deaths
then my sadness would be enough to bring them to life again.
In other words, Khalid(خالد) is saying I am in pain for the ones that I lost from my army.
I'm having a lot of sorrow for that.
But what will sorrow do?
If sorrow would bring them back to life, I would have done that. And then he said;
ولقد إقتحمت حتى أن يسم الحياء و ان قنت بالموت
And I would throw myself among their ranks, until I would become certain
that I would die and I would give up living.
Khalid(خالد) is saying that I have put myself in situations where I would lose hope in living
and see death as a certainty meaning Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
and this would respond to the orientalist
who say Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was looking after pleasure
Khalid(خالد) was saying that I have sought after death.
I have thrown myself among them, to die.
Nevertheless, I wouldn't get it.
And At-Tabari(ألطبري) would say
that when Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) would throw himself among the enemy
ياكلو كل شيءٍ أمامة
He would eat everything around him, everything around him would just fall down dead.
Khalid(خالد) was looking for death, but nobody could kill him.
So Khalid(خالد) was saying;
حتى أن قنت موت
I'm not entangled to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا)
there is no Tathaqul Ilad-Duniyah(تثاكل إلى الدنيا) with Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه.
In fact, let me mention this to you, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) marrying twice and it might be interpreted otherwise.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), this is his own statement. He said:
If a beautiful woman, whom I love is married to me
or I am given the news of a newborn male child that is less dearer to my heart,
then sleeping in a tent, in a cold windy night, planning to ambush my enemy the next day.
Now I want the single brothers to think about that.
The ones, who want to get married you know how much you love marriage
you are so eager to get married. Khalid(خالد) is saying that
me being married to a woman, whom I love is less dear to my heart
than spending the night in a cold tent planning to attack my enemy.
Do you understand what that means?
The next day he could be dead.
Plus he is a leader of an army
and a leader of army bears the responsibility of any loss that happens.
I mean, you can't show your face to the Muslims after you lost, it's shame.
Before a person is giving a speech or before a person is going to a very important deal.
Their heart is pounding, they feel pain in their guts, butterflies in their stomach
because of the presence of the situation.
Can you think about Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) planning an attack for the next day?
But that is more dear to him, than marriage.
That's how much they love Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله), they love Shahadah(شَهَادَة).
And then he said because Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said that you were tricked by Maja'ah(مجاعة). He said:
وأمَّا خَدَعت مجاعة إيَّائ أن راعي إني لم أختي رائي يومي
ولم يكل لي علم با لغيب وقد صنع الله للمسلمين خيرًا
And saying that Maja'ah(مجاعة) tricked me.
My opinion was not wrong on that day and I do not know the unseen.
Khalid(خالد) is saying I base my opinion according to what I can see and I don't know the unseen.
وقد صنع الله للمسلمين خيرًا
And Allah has done the Muslims good, they have won, and the end belongs to Al-Muttaqeen(ألمتقين).
We have achieved victory, so.
Yes, Maja'ah(مجاعة) did trick me, but his people became Muslim
because Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) it is mentioned At-Tabari(ألطبري) that
he sent a letter to Khalid(خالد), telling him:
Whoever lands in your hand from the people of Abu Hanifa(أبوحنيفه), execute them.
But he received this letter after he already executed the truce between him and Maja'ah(مجاعة).
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) wanted to punish the Murtaddeen(مرتدين) severely.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, His Qadar(قَدَر) is that Maja'ah(مجاعة) and his people became Muslim.
When Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) received the letter, that soften his heart a bit.
But then there are some people from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and also Abu Barzal-Aslami(أبوبرزلأسلمي), who came to argue on behalf of Khalid(خالد).
He said, Abu Barzal-Aslami(أبوبرزلأسلمي), he said: O Khalifah(خليفه) of the Messenger of Allah,
Khalid(خالد) cannot be characterized as having of lacking courage
or of betraying his trust to the Muslims.
Khalid(خالد) has searched has put himself in situations in search of martyrdom, and he did his best but he won.
And the truce that he concluded with the people was a pleasing truce to him.
And you cannot say that his view was wrong
because he saw women covering the roofs, and he thought that they were men.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) said: I believe what you say
and you have given me a more valid excuse for Khalid(خالد) than his letter.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) saw that this is more of an excuse for Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
and the issue was over with
and Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه forgave, Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه ورضي الله عنهم أجمعين.
Last thing regarding the Yamamah(يمامة).
When the news reached the Muslims
وإستحر قتل في حافظة القرآن
There are so many Huffaaz(حفاظ) of Qur'an killed.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه went to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
it show you how drastic that event was?
He went to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and said,
There were so many of the Sahabah(صحابه) the memorize of Qur'an who were killed
and Qur'an is in the hearts of men and if the men go, then Qur'an might be lost.
So why don't you compile Qur'an?
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: How can you ask me to do something that Rasool Allah ﷺ did not do?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) argued with him.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه thought over it
and he came to adopt the opinion of Umar(عُمَر).
So, Zaid Bin Thabit Al-Ansaari(زيد بن ثابت ألأنصاري) a 21 year old young man from Al-Ansaar(اَلْاَنْصَار) received a message saying that the Khalifah(خليفه) wants to meet you.
He's narrating that he said: I go to meet the Khalifah(خليفه)
and I find Umar(عُمَر) sitting next to him. And then the Khalifah(خليفه) tells me:
Umar(عُمَر) came to me and told me that there are many Huffaz(حفاظ) of Qur'an, who were killed.
So why don't you compile Qur'an to protect it?
So I told them: This is something that Rasool Ullah did not do.
But then I thought about it, and came to agree with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
So now I am giving you the responsibility of compiling Al-Qur'an.
Zaid Bin Thabit(زيد بن ثابت) said: If Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) would load on top of my shoulders, a mountain
it would be lighter in weight than the mission he gave to me.
But Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: The reason why I'm appointing you to do that he said;
وانك رجل شاب عاقل لا نتحمك وقد كنت تكتب الوحي ألي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
You are a young man, you are mature and wise, and we trust you for this mission
and you used to write the revelation for Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And Zaid Bin Thabit(زيد بن ثابت) was one of the scholars of Qur'an even though he was at that young age.
So he said;
I had to go around collecting Qur'an from the hearts of men
and collecting all of the manuscripts of Qur'an that existed.
He picked up Usub(عصب)
Usub(عصب) is palm leaves, they use to write on palm leaves
and they use to write on flat, carved rock and they use write on the shoulder bone of camels.
The shoulder bone is a flat plate, so they would write on that plate.
And they would also write on leather.
So he said: I had to gather all of those pieces and then I compiled the Qur'an.
And the Mus'haf(مصحف), the original copy was with Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق), until he passed away.
It was handed down to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
And when Umar(عُمَر) passed away it was given to Hafsa(حفصه),
the daughter of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه, Umm-Ul-Mo'mineen(أم المؤمنين).
So that was the story of the beginning of the compiling of Qur'an.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ